Guide to the Carl Gustav Hempel Papers, 1903-1997 ASP.1999.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Teaching [RESTRICTED], 1937-1985; IV.
  - Teaching Material According to Course Numbers, 1939-1985; 1.
    - Phil 101: Introduction to Philosophy: Notes for Chapter on Ethics, 1966 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Phil 531: Basic Problems in the Methodology of the Natural and Social Sciences (Princeton), 1953-1965 (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - Phil 531 (523): Philosophy of Science, 1959-1963 (Box 78, Folder 2)
    - Phil 531: Graduate Course in Philosophy of Science, 1953-1973 (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Phil 531: Graduate Seminar Spring, Student Evaluations, 1969-1973 (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Phil 531: Philosophy of Science, Spring 1973, and Phil. 290-4 "Analytic Empiricist Perspectives on Science in the Light of Recent Criticism," Berkeley 1975, 1973-1977 (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - Phil 531: Student Papers, Spring 1973 (Box 78, Folder 6)
    - Phil 531: Problems of Empiricism, Aufbau, Theories, 1973 (Box 78, Folder 7)
    - Phil 531: Student Evaluations Princeton: Graduate Seminar, Fall 1973, 1973-1974 (Box 78, Folder 8)
    - Phil 531: Graduate Course in Philosophy of Science (Isolated sentences and paper by Glenn Kessler), 1973-1976 (Box 78, Folder 9)
    - Phil 531: Selected Problems of Empiricism, Hebrew University March-July '74 and Princeton Fall '74, 1974 (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - Phil 531: Papers Railton, Fall 1974, 1974-1975 (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - Phil 531: Student Evaluations Princeton: Graduate Seiminar Philosophy 531, 1974-1976 (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - Phil 288 (287/531): Seminars "Exploration", Notes and Term Papers, 1977-1979, 1982, 1977-1982 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - Phil 288: Philosophy of the Natural and Social Sciences, Fall 1978 (Box 80, Folder 2)
    - Phil 288: Philosophy of the Natural and Social Sciences, Explanation, Course Records, Roster, Student Reports, Notes on Reports, Grades, Fall 1979 (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - Phil 288: Scientific Explanation, Course Records, Syllabus, Grade Records, Records of Student Work, Winter 1982 (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - Phil 288 (287, 531): Explanation, Notes, and Materials for Grad. course, Winter 1982, 1977-1982 (Box 80, Folder 5)
  - Teaching Material in Chronological Order, 1937-1978; 2.
    - Phil 45b: Philosophy of Mathematics, 1937-1955 (Box 81, Folder 1)
    - Notes and Exams on "Probability and Induction," and Hempel's Notes on Carnap Research-Seminar "Probability-Logic," May 1938, 1938-1951 (Box 81, Folder 2)
    - Harvard University, Carnap, Philosophy 3b2 Final Exam, 1940-1941 (Box 81, Folder 3)
    - Phil 12: Advanced Logic (Notes Destroyed; Based on Tarski), Syllabi, Reading Lists & Tests, 1941-1945 (Box 81, Folder 4)
    - Phil 12: Symbolic Logic, Course Notes, undated (Box 81, Folder 5)
    - Queens College, Phil 9: Final Exams and Notes, 1941-1947 (Box 81, Folder 6)
    - Math 17: Fundamental Concepts of Mathematics, Notes, Tests, and Final Exams, 1943-1947 (Box 81, Folder 7)
    - Math 17: Fundamental Concepts, Part I and II, undated (Box 81, Folder 8)
    - Math 17: Fundamental Concepts, Part I and II, undated (Box 81, Folder 9)
    - Phil 19b: Intermediate Logic, Combined with Phil 10 Notes, 1944-1952 (Box 81, Folder 10)
    - Phil 253: Empiricism Notes, 1945-1955 (Box 81, Folder 11)
    - Course on Probability and Induction, 1946-1954 (Box 81, Folder 12)
    - Yale Phil 10, Princeton Phil 201: Philosophy Tests, Elementary Logic:, 1947-1965 (Box 82, Folder 1)
    - Yale, Phil 142a: Philosophy of Empiricism, 1948-1949 (Box 82, Folder 2)
    - Yale, Phil 37a: Philosophy of Science Tests, 1948-1952 (Box 82, Folder 3)
    - Yale, Phil 37: Philosophy of Science Tests, 1949-1950 (Box 82, Folder 4)
    - Final Examination in "Philosophy of Nature", 1949 (Box 82, Folder 5)
    - Yale, Material on Various Courses, 1949-1950 (Box 82, Folder 6)
    - Yale, Phil 113a: Principles of Concept Formation in the Natural Sciences, 1949-1950 (Box 82, Folder 7)
    - Phil 25b: Intermediate Logic, 1949 and 1951 (Box 82, Folder 8)
    - Phil 25: Deductive Logic, Course Notes, 1949-1952 (Box 82, Folder 9)
    - Evaluations by Students of Courses Hempel Taught, 1949-1955 (Box 82, Folder 10)
    - Philosophy of Mathematics, Part I and II, 1949-1955 (Box 82, Folder 11)
    - Philosophy of Mathematics, Part I and II, 1949-1955 (Box 82, Folder 12)
    - Yale, Phil 142b: Selected Problems of Empiricism, 1950 (Box 82, Folder 13)
    - Phil 10: Elementary Logic, Course Notes, 1950 (Box 82, Folder 14)
    - Yale, Phil 110b: Philosophy of Empiricism, 1951 (Box 82, Folder 15)
    - Grünbaum, Lehigh University, Phil 261: Philosophy of Science Tests, 1951-1952 (Box 83, Folder 1)
    - Yale, Phil 113b: Principles of Concept Formation, 1952 (Box 83, Folder 2)
    - Harvard, Phil 253: Seminar in Problems of Empiricism, 1953-1954 (Box 83, Folder 3)
    - Harvard, Phil 140: Deductive Logic, 1951-1954 (Box 83, Folder 4)
    - Harvard, Phil 140: Deductive Logic, 1951-1954 (Box 83, Folder 5)
    - Havard, Phil 141:, 1953-1954 (Box 83, Folder 6)
    - Harvard, Phil 181: Course Description and Tests, 1953-1954 (Box 83, Folder 7)
    - Harvard, Probability Course Spring 1954, 1954-1957 (Box 83, Folder 8)
    - Harvard, Probability Course Spring 1954, 1954-1957 (Box 83, Folder 9)
    - Harvard, Probability Course Spring 1954, 1954-1957 (Box 83, Folder 10)
    - Exam Sheets & Drafts by Hempel and Others, 1953-1973 (Box 84, Folder 1)
    - Yale, Phil 296a: Contemporary Empiricism, 1954-1955 (Box 84, Folder 2)
    - Yale, Phil 360a: Explanation and Understanding in the Natural and Social Sciences, 1954-1955 (Box 84, Folder 3)
    - Yale, Phil 39b: Logic of the Social Sciences, 1955 (Box 84, Folder 4)
    - Princeton, Phil 249, 1955 (Box 84, Folder 5)
    - Princeton, Phil 523: Problems of Philosophy, Problems of Empiricism, 1955 and 1963 (Box 84, Folder 6)
    - Senior Seminars:, Fall Terms 1957, 1960, 1961, 1964 (Box 84, Folder 7)
    - Introduction to Philosophy of Science, 1957-1973 (Box 84, Folder 8)
    - Phil 528: Theory of Knowledge, Fall 1958 (Box 84, Folder 9)
    - Materials for a Seminar on Induction & Acceptance Spring 1971(incl. Notes for Earlier Seminars), 1964-1971 (Box 84, Folder 10)
    - Course Materials Carlton 1976 and Berkeley 1975, 1975-1976 (Box 84, Folder 11)
    - Hebrew University: Philosophy of Science, 1974 (Box 84, Folder 12)
    - UC Berkeley, Phil 290-4: Analytic Empiricist Perspectives on Science in the Light of Recent Criticism, Winter 1974-1975 (Box 84, Folder 13)
    - Carleton College, Notes for Phil 51: "The Epistemology of Logical Empiricism", 1976 (Box 84, Folder 14)
    - Berkeley, Phil 290-5: "Scientific Theorizing, Scientific Rationality, and 'Rational Reconstruction'", 1977 (Box 84, Folder 15)
    - Berkeley, Phil 138: "Introduction to the Philosophy of the Natural & Social Sciences", Winter 1977 (Box 84, Folder 16)
    - UC Irvine, Humanities 198: "Varieties of Scientific Understanding", Spring 1978 (Box 84, Folder 17)
  - Reference Literature and Reprints Used for Teaching, 3.
    - Achinstein—Barker (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - Bergmann and Spence; Bromberger, Canfield, Dray; and Eberle, Kaplan, and Montague (Box 85, Folder 2)
    - Fain—Feigl (Box 85, Folder 3)
    - Grünbaum—Helmer and Rescher (Box 85, Folder 4)
    - Hempel (Box 85, Folder 5)
    - Hempel (Box 86, Folder 01-02)
    - Kaplan—Nagel (Box 86, Folder 3)
    - Popper—Rynin (Box 86, Folder 4)
    - Salmon—Wigner (Box 86, Folder 5)
    - Reading Lists and Exams from Adolf Grünbaum, C.K. Wilber, and others, 1980-1981 (Box 87, Folder 1)
    - Phil 531: Reference Materials,1956-1981 (Box 87, Folder 02-03)
    - Graduate Seminars Reprints and Literature A-R, 1956-1981 (Box 87, Folder 04-07)
    - Graduate Seminars Reprints and Literature S-Z, 1959-1978 (Box 88, Folder 1)
    - Literature Ad Philosophy of Social and Behavioral Science, 1958-1971 (Box 88, Folder 2)
    - Readings Lists of Courses by Hempel and Others (142b Selected Problems), 1954-1962 (Box 88, Folder 3)
    - Readings (Reprints) for Φ531, 1948-1988 (Box 88, Folder 4)
    - Reprints for Use in Introductory Philosophy of Science Courses, B-W, 1930-1977 (Box 88, Folder 05-06)
    - Reprints of Articles by Hempel for Use in Courses, 1948-1984 (Box 88, Folder 7)
  - Dissertations, 1954-1984; 5.
    Some dissertation contain handwritten and typed inserts by Hempel and others.
    - Bachmann, Friedrich. "Untersuchen zur Grundlegung der Arithmetik mit besonderer Beziehung auf Dedekind/Frege und Russell", 1934 (Box 89, Folder 1)
    - Brown, Lee Miller. " The Sufficiency of Nomological Subsumption for the Explanation of Events", 1986 (Box 89, Folder 2)
    - Bohnert, Herbert. "The Interpretation of Theory" (with inserts), 1961 (Box 89, Folder 3)
    - Fetzer, James H. "The Statistician's Dilemma: A Study in the Logic of Concept Formation", 1970 (Box 89, Folder 4)
    - Hoffman, Lester Victor. "Crucial Issues in Explanation: The Content, Scope, and Method of the Nomological Theory", 1970 (Box 89, Folder 5)
    - Jeffrey, Richard C. "Contributions to the Theory of Inductive Probability", 1957 (Box 89, Folder 6)
    - Maher, Patrick. "Rationality and Belief", 1984 (Box 89, Folder 7)
    - Massey, Gerald J. "The Philosophy of Space," (with inserts), 1963 (Box 89, Folder 8)
    - Matheson, Gordon. "The Concept of Analyticity," (with inserts), 1954 (Box 89, Folder 9)
    - McCord, Edward LeRoy. "The Groundwork of Cultural Anthropology", 1980 (Box 89, Folder 10)
    - Santoro, Maria Rosa. "La spiegazione storica nell'analisi di C.G. Hempel", 1971-1972 (Box 89, Folder 11)
    - Railton, Peter Albert. " Explaining Explanation: A Realist Account of Scientific Explanation and Understanding, 1980 (Box 90, Folder 1-5)
  - 2022 Addition [Closed], 1940-1973
    - Grade Books [Closed], 1940-1973 (Box 92)
- Audio Recordings, V.
  - Books in Study, Boxes 1-12/12-22, Periodicals B23-6, Letters Box 27-8 (Box 91, Cassette 1)
  - Books in Study, Boxes 43/58, Periodicals, Letters B29 (Box 91, Cassette 2)
  - Books in Study, B69/71 (Box 91, Cassette 3)
  - Probability (Rand) Sides 1,2,3 (Box 91, Cassette 4)
  - Side Record 4 Side 1,2 (Box 91, Cassette 5)
  - Record 7 Sides 1,2; Record 8 Sides 1,2 (Box 91, Cassette 6)
  - Record 9 Sides 1,2; Caruso Bois Epais Not Recorded (Box 91, Cassette 7)
  - Sides 1-4 Roots of Philo Error Hans Reichenbach; Sides 5-7 (8 Incomplete) (Box 91, Cassette 8)
  - Sides 8,9,11 Roots of Philo. Error Hans Reichenbach (Box 91, Cassette 9)
  - Philosophilical Implications of Science Sides 1,2; 3,4 (Box 91, Cassette 10)
  - Report on Conversations w/ Bohr & Einstein 1,2 H. Reichenbach (Box 91, Cassette 11)
  - Kant & der deutsche Idealismus (in German) 1,2 H. Reichenbach; 3,4 (Box 91, Cassette 12)
  - Explanation; Conversation Between Hume-Russel, Letter to B. Russel (Box 91, Cassette 13)
  - Quantum Mechanics Sides 1-3; 4-6 (Box 91, Cassette 14)
  - Mr. & Mrs. Phillip Frank; Quantum Mechanics Sides 7,8 (Box 91, Cassette 15)
  - Interview with Carl G. Hempel in his office (1009D CL) on March 17, 1982 at 10 AM, 1982-03-17 (Box 91, Cassette 16)
    Related Materials
    Transcript in Box 51, Folder 5.
  - Hempel 3/24/82 (Original), 1982-03-24 (Box 91, Cassette 17)
  - Side One Only. Hempel Interview in his office on August 1,1983, 1983-08-01 (Box 91, Cassette 18)
  - Hempel's Talk Rudolf Carnap, Logical Empiricist, at the Joint APA-ASL Symposium on Rudolf Carnap, Los Angeles, March 26, 1971 (Box 91, Disk 19)
    Acquisition Information
    Gift of Alex Bellamy, London School of Economics, on January 20, 2006.
- Offprints, c. 1930s-1980s; VI.
  - Hempel Offprints, 1931-1984 (Box 94)
  - Annotated Offprints, A-D, c. 1940s-1980s (Box 95)
  - Annotated Offprints, E-Feuer, c. 1940s-1980s (Box 96)
  - Annotated Offprints, Feyerabend-G, c. 1940s-1980s (Box 97)
  - Annotated Offprints, H-O, c. 1940s-1980s (Box 98)
  - Annotated Offprints, P-Z, c. 1940s-1980s (Box 99)